[Music]
topology and geometry the zero section
is about solving problems
by a method characteristic of topology
and that's by
deformation what do we mean by
this let's start with a rather silly
example but an instructive
one it's due
to poya one of the most original
mathematicians of the 20th century are
Hungarian originally he spent most of
his career later life in at
Stanford consider a
dis I'm going to call those two points
on the boundary a and one point here B
one point here C and one point here B
and one point here C okay
question can you connect
this a to
a b to B and C to C by continuous curves
within the dis of course
in such a way that the connecting curves
that you
use do not
intercept avoid
[Applause]
intercepting if you can please show me
how if you cannot if you can prove that
it's impossible please tell me why it's
impossible go ahead and
work so you might connect this to this
by some curve B to b c to C but those
curves should not intersect is that
possible if it's possible please show me
how and if it's impossible please tell
me why it's impossible you should try to
figure it
out so either you should be drawing a
picture showing that it's possible or if
you are not drawing a picture at this
very moment for example you are not
drawing a picture then you should be
thinking about how to prove that it's
impossible yeah either you believe it's
possible in which case you should be
drawing a picture right now yeah if you
are not drawing a picture that means you
believe it's impossible and you're
trying to prove
that thank you so is there some
extra I might as well keep an
ex
no that's outside so somebody drew a
curve like this and that's that's
illegal also if you draw a curve like
this that's also
illegal on the disc so inside the
this yeah so outside this this this this
pie very nice green land outside there's
a sea and lots of sharks and you don't
want to go
there
[Music]
have you
finished life is short so we should get
working
quickly ah that looks okay so finish the
job what what are you waiting
for huh oh really okay that's
interesting have you
finished I'll give you 30 more seconds
you think it's impossible
okay
that's what do you
think okay that looks good what do you
think let's get working there are people
who haven't drawn anything no you have
to keep drawing draw lots of pictures
it's possible you think there's people
who have proved that it's impossible and
there are people who have proved that
it's possible
huh has anybody proved that it's both
possible and impossible
okay okay let's discuss the solution
before we do so let me ask do people
feel that they have had enough time to
think about
this yes good some
people might feel that they haven't had
enough time well okay it's nice to be
able to think for a long time
but try to get
going this is a strange advice because I
think everyone tells you that oh you can
take your time and you can but life is
short also I'm with you for 3 weeks only
and you know you want to get ah head in
your careers so sometimes if you just
sit down and start
working you can finish in 5 minutes
whereas if you say okay uh
where is my
pen and where was my paper so you spend
about half an hour before the other
people have finished already five or six
projects okay so let's get going
now it looks
impossible indeed if you draw a curve
between a and a whatever curve you
draw it's intuitive and it's through the
this curve divid the dis into two parts
and then you
cannot put B and B together or C and C
together you might say okay what if I
do this ah so that's more problem
because now I can connect B and B but
still C and C cannot be connected if you
connect them you have to intersect the
curve that have so let's think about it
in the following
way you say this problem looks difficult
let's deform the
problem so that it's easier to solve it
sounds like
cheating but it's not cheap this is a
this is a that's
B that's C okay here we have B here we
have C let's bring these around like
this okay so that c comes here and B
comes here let's call them C Prime and B
Prime in this configuration you think
you can solve the problem I think I
can so what we are going to do is
connect this connect this and then
connect
this
but it's not the same problem yes it's
not the same problem because we deform
the
problem so let's deform it
back what did we do to deform this
program to this program we just turn
them around let's now imagine that those
red curves are made of
elastic and so is the yellow one and
move these
over so what's going to happen I shall
show you the picture in the intermediate
stage this is a this is a this is B and
this is C intermediate stage is when B
is traveling like this and it's dragging
this curve like that and C is traveling
like this and draging the curve like
this and this yellow curve is sort of
like
this and then you keep pushing pushing
pushing and you realize that it is
possible supp to solve this problem
because at the end you get this curve
and this curve excuse me
and you are
not
okay it's very
interesting
you this is called solving the problem
by deformation what are the steps first
the problem looks difficult so you say
is there an easy problem I can solve and
if that easier version can be reached
from your original Problem by a
continuous
deformation that's great news because
you can probably apply topology to solve
the problem or at least to make the
problem more accessible more productive
so what you do you deform the problem to
the easier version solve the problem and
bring the problem back solution back to
the original one that's what we should
do for this I would like to suggest a
further reading and that's the left half
of the sheet that I handed out further
Reading Please read the section it's a
little complicated but I'm sure you can
read it in the book by Arnold a great
Russian mathematician who pass by not
long ago and O you know what this stands
for ordinary differential equations yeah
that's the title and chapter one section
two it's this sheet that I handed out
the left half of the sheet it's very
interesting the problem invented by
Constantino now there are several
English translations of this book if you
can read Russian that's great it's
originally Russian but if you do not um
there's a translation yellow translation
by Springer fa Edition but it's not a
good translation you should it also use
the translation by Richard Silverman
he's one of the greatest possibly the
greatest translator of Russian
mathematics into
English and he has a translation from
the MIT press you might be able to find
it online as well and so use this
translation that's a very beautiful very
complex translation our
not let's move on another
example if you have two circles on the
plane
to intersecting
circles have what is called a common
core in
English what do we mean by a c this is
what we mean by a c okay those two
intersection points are linked by a
single line segment if you like and
that's called a pord
okay come on for um good good
night now please draw
three circles any three circles that
that are
intersecting with each
other
okay and corresponding to those three
circles we can draw the three
chords there is this common
cord
and this common cord and finally this
common
cord theorem those three cores always
meing a point
simple
PP that's an abbreviation very standard
abbreviation by English speaking
mathematicians for
point so from now on I'll use this
abbreviation
why why is this why do they mean after
all if you draw three random cirle
random NES as you done yesterday they
don't meit in a single point
so it is a miracle that those three
lines meet in a single point why does
this miracle happen any
[Applause]
ideas let's deform the
problem but here we are not sure how to
deform it
the kind of information that we'll make
is an extraordinary information we shall
go into higher dimensional
space sometimes a problem in 2D two
dimensional problem is difficult but if
you lift it come out into the
threedimensional space it becomes easy
sometimes the problem in
threedimensional space is difficult but
if you go into the four dimensional
space it suddenly becomes easy and so we
want to deform the problem
but by escaping into higher Dimensions
interesting let me show you what I
mean those are
[Music]
the two circles right but please imagine
that these are not pictures of two
circles but pictures of two
spheres that you're are seeing from
above okay and they're intersecting each
other so in practice what you are going
to see is a
picture like
this yeah can you see this picture as
I'm seeing those are two spheres that
are intersecting entering each other
they
intersect
okay so if you have three of
those imagine three three spheres let's
say that their centers are on the same
plane on the same level but let's say
that they're all intersecting each
other then what do we get you
get a picture like
this picture like
this and picture like
this can you see the picture as I'm
seeing those are three
and they are entering each
other okay and if you see them from
above this is what you'll see well what
does this line correspond it's not
actually a line it's part of a circle
that you're seeing from above because if
you have one sphere on this side another
sphere on this side and if you're
looking at the intersection they
intersect along a circle and if you see
it from in front from your side you
think that it's a looks like a line
similarly this is a circle this is a
circle but look if if you have three
spheres here here here middle small
large if you like there will be a point
in the Middle where they all come
together right a dip if you like if you
um drop some water from Above This is
where the water will make a little
puddle okay but if you now think of it
as two dimensional picture that
means that
those three
hores
and intersecting in this single
point
Q did you
follow
no did you follow to this point so
instead of thinking that you have two
circles with a common cord please think
of these as spheres we are now thinking
of them as threedimensional
pictures except that you are looking at
them from above so you think there's a
straight line but this is actually not a
straight line line it's the appearance
of a straight line but in fact it's a
circular intersection that you see are
you following so far okay now look
at this
picture this sphere and this sphere
intersect along this circular
intersection this sphere and this sphere
along this this sphere and this sphere
and this sphere along this but look if
you have three spheres that are meeting
entering each other somewhere in the
middle there will be a point at which
the those three circles all come
together right you can see this because
you have lived in this world for more
than 20 years or whatever so if you if
you drop water from above there will be
some water there yeah that point now you
remember that this is a threedimensional
picture but projected on the two
dimensional picture you think of it as a
3D picture and then L and behold it's
exactly that
picture end of the demonstration proof
finished
[Music]
QED so it's a wonderful method all you
did we don't we don't seem to have done
anything all you did was to come out of
2D look at the picture in 3D and say Ah
that's obvious and went back to the
2D so this is another kind of
deformation by lifting the problem out
into higher dimensions and we shall see
this time and and again so so the
solution
is is to lift a
picture in three dimensional
space so that's all there is okay and a
further reading that I would like to
suggest is on the right half of the
sheet
that Theo section problem is taken from
another marvelous book collection of
essays and anecdotes and little problems
by a great English mathematician from
this first half of the 20th century most
littlewood and it's called littlewood in
bothos O and Mr in the as Library I
couldn't find the MIT press translation
I know but you might be able to find it
on line as I
say
[Applause]
okay it is now possible to
State
formally maybe I can write on that PL
too can you see from that distance
okay I'll try to write a little
larger and then come back
to this is very important so I'm going
to point that it is
important it's very
important basic
strategy
larer
for applying
topology all sorts of
signs the situation is this often you
have a
problem that you want to solve you want
to make progress on maybe you want to um
investigate aspects of this problem to
see what it can tell us but this problem
is often very complic
licated
Difficult by degeneracy do you know what
I mean by De generais for example you
calculate the determinant of a matrix
and it's zero Ah that's bad because I
cannot invert The
Matrix or some function derivative
becomes zero that's okay perhaps but the
second derivative also becomes zero ah
so I cannot tell whether it's maximum or
minimum I have to do something else so
all these are degeneracies unfortunate
circumstances that make your problem
difficult
DeGeneres so what do we do well if
you're an optimist and if you're a
topologist and if you know mod ma mod
mathematics you deform the
problem yeah to a generic
situation
free from
degeneracies and then this situation has
a simple
solution as we did in example one we
just deform the problem and that deform
the problem easy solution we lifted the
second example to three space and
threedimensional version of the problem
is very easy but
but as as complained that's not the
solution to the original problem but
with some luck you can deform back this
deform back this
solution to obtain the solution to the
original
problem when trying to go directly from
the problem to the solution might be
impossible oh very very and you don't
have thus you deform the problem to
something simpler something more generic
I shall explain time and again what we
mean by generic generic simple so it in
that context in that situation and then
deform the solution back and obtain the
solution to the original difficult
problem that's the basic strategy that's
the basic skem for applying topology to
all s of mathematical problems and
Beyond
okay let's
note that sometimes you can use the same
strategy can people in the carb see what
I WR here if I write enough so
note that
sometimes we can use the same
method approach
to
show that some problems are impossible
solve that's
also a useful piece of information that
your problem is unsolvable so that you
don't have to waste any any more time or
you have to change the problem
completely and go on to work on
something more
productive okay here here an
example let's
take example three I'll write a little
larg so from the back example three
let's say that P and Q are two
matrices over the same size Square
matrices of size n by n okay so n by n
Square
matrices
okay now as you know P * Q The Matrix
modifcation and Q * P are in general not
equal most often they
not
[Applause]
yeah however there's something that this
PQ and this QP share something in common
and that is the IG values
but show
that PQ and QP they
have the same Ang
vales let's try
to I open some
parentheses in the course of this
lecture I'll say sometimes things that
you may not understand if I'm speaking
unclearly or if my English is bad or if
you have fallen asleep and just woke up
please tell me and I'll be very happy to
repeat and explain but sometimes I might
be discussing material that comes from
parts of science that you have never met
before something that's unknown to you
then don't worry too much I have
designed a course so that even if you
skip those parts the rest will make
sense and will be very useful if you
want you can come and talk with me and
I'll be very happy to help you but some
of you may most of you will be
comfortable but some of you may be
uncomfortable with I values well okay
don't worry too much about it but most
of you will have used lots and lots of
techniques involving I values okay so
they have the same a values let's call
this statement star because I'm going to
refer okay here is a proposed
[Music]
solution can you see from the back
still can you
okay look at
PQ and notice that if I multiply from
the right by Q inverse and from the left
by
Q well that becomes Q * P * Q * Q
inverse it becomes
QP ah but that means that PQ as a matrix
and qt are related by this relationship
that you multiply in front and in back
by some Matrix and it's inverse and so
they're called similar matrices or
conjugate matrices or geometrically
speaking PQ and
QP are two matrices for the same linear
transformation they are just two
different Matrix representations of the
same geometric object which is the
linear transformation just with respect
to different
bases
transformation and the change of basis
Matrix is Q okay so because the same
linear trans has of course the same I
values this hold is true
QED it's not quite
QED there is
somebody like alak who is going to
complain that I solved the problem which
is simpler than the original problem
because this argument Works only when Q
is
invertible what if Q does not have an
inverse what if Q is degener then I
cannot use this
[Music]
argument
Works
only when in the lucky circumstances
when Q is invertable in other
words q inverse
EXs or if you
like only
when the determinant of Q is non
zero but i' like to ask you okay people
complain that it doesn't work because
determinant Q might be zero but what are
the chances that the determinant Q is
exactly
zero
I mean take a matrix and suppose that
its determinant is
zero then change the entries of the
Matrix a little bit slightly here and
there do you think the determinant will
stay zero no it's not going to be zero
on the other hand suppose that the
Matrix has a nonzero determinant let's
say its value is 0.148 or something like
this and then you change the entries of
the Matrix slightly with the determinant
still be know zero yes I think so so the
situation where the determinant is zero
is
degenerate situation where the
determinant is non zero this useful
situation is a generic situation it's a
general situation it's the situation
that happens most often in the majority
of cases so you think aha I can apply
topology so how shall we go about
this we
note that that Q is
invertible in most
situations in the precise sense
that if Q is invertible to begin
with then any small paration small
enough part
of Q remain
invertable so it's a stable property if
you
like small parations neighborhood of
this Q have the same property whereas if
Q is not invertible non noninvertible
that's when determinant is
zero then small paration of
Q become
in it might be even better to draw a
picture for this so I
sh